Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Articles/Chapters/Papers
  - Sheridan, Eugene R. "Captain Smith Goes to Jamestown." Documentary Editing 10, no. 2 (June 1988): 11-15; illus., 694
    A favorable review of Philip L. Barbour's 1986 edition of John Smith's Complete Works. Also includes concise summaries of Smith's life and of the controversy in more recent times over his reliability as a chronicler of historyIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Shiner, Joel Lewis. "Early Cemetery on 'Third Ridge' at Jamestown." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 65 (1957): 150-53; illus., 695
    "Excavations made in 1955 at the site of the third and fourth statehouses at Jamestown were designed to locate the graves under and near the foundations and to discover as much as possible about the area."
  - Shirley, John W. "George Percy at Jamestown, 1607-1612." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 57 (1949): 227-43., 696
    An account, based on Percy family papers, of the "highest-born gentleman of the settlement at Jamestown," who served as President and Deputy GovernorIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Sieche, Erwin F. "Austria-Hungary's Last Naval Visit to the USA." Warship International 27 (1990): 142-64., 697
    Lists all voyages in the Western Hemisphere by ships of the Austro-Hungarian navy and describes the visit of the two-ship Austro-Hungarian squadron to the 1907 Jamestown Tercentennial Exposition as recorded in the diary of Ludwig Ritter von Hoehnel (1857-1942), the commander of one of the ships, who had gained fame earlier as an African explorer.
  - Silver, Marc. "Pocahontas, for Real." U. S. News and World Report 118 (19 June 1995): 61-64; illus., 698
    Visiting the Jamestown area can help dispel the myths about Pocahontas that are portrayed in a recent motion picture.
  - Slezkin, L. "Legenda o Dzhone Smite ili pervye gody Dzheimstauna." (The Legend of John Smith, or the Early Years of Jamestown). Novaia i Noveishaia Istoriia 1973, no. 3: 159-70., 699
    Discusses several incidents in Smith's published accounts in an attempt to assess his veracity. Concludes that Smith was not a hero and that he manufactured part of the legendIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Stevenson, Robert. "American Musical Scholarship: Parker to Thayer." 19th Century Music 1 (March 1978): 191-210., 700
    Presents information concerning the musical life of the seventeenth, eighteenth, and nineteenth centuries in Florida, New Mexico, and Virginia (Jamestown and Richmond), and in Massachusetts in the eighteenth century.
  - Surrender of Virginia to the Parliamentary Commissioners, March, 1651-2. Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 11 (1903): 32-41., 701
    Includes a report of the commissioners and abstracts of other papers in the Library of Virginia.
  - Taylor, Robert T. "The Jamestown Tercentennial Exposition of 1907." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 65 (1957): 169-208; illus., 702
  - Terman, C. Richard, and Robert J. Huggett. "Occurrence of Kepone in White-footed Mice (Peromyscus leucopus noveboracensis) on Jamestown Island, Virginia." 58th Annual Meeting of the Virginia Academy of Science, Charlottesville, May 13-16, 1980., 703
    Levels of Kepone found in the livers of white-footed mice on Jamestown Island were significantly greater than levels in mice in an inland control area at the College of William and Mary. These data are the first indicating Kepone contamination of small terrestrial mammalsThe authors published an article by the same title in Environment International 3 (1980): 307-10.
  - Thorndale, William. "The Virginia Census of 1619." Magazine of Virginia Genealogy 33 (1995): 155-70., 704
    Provides transcriptions of manuscripts from the Ferrar Papers at Magdalene College, Cambridge. The total population of James Citty in March 1618/19 was 117 according to these documentsIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Thornton, J. Mills, III. "The Thrusting Out of Governor Harvey: A Seventeenth-Century Rebellion." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 76 (1968): 11-26., 705
  - Thurman, Melburn D. "Experimental Archaeology and Woodland Indian Houses." Archeological Society of Virginia Quarterly Bulletin 41 (1986): 89-96., 706
    Discusses the limits of ethnohistorical sources in helping to reconstruct the Late Woodland house model in an exhibit at Virginia Beach. The article is followed by an exchange of replies between Errett Callahan and Steve W. Edwards (pp. 97-111). Callahan answers Thurman's criticisms of a 1985 paper written by Callahan. Edwards claims that Callahan compromised the larger goals of Jamestown Settlement's living history exhibit by applying overly exacting standards to the replication of the Indian village there. Callahan suggests ways of achieving greater accuracy without jeopardizing the accessibility and goals of the Jamestown project.
  - Travis Family. William and Mary Quarterly, 1st ser., 18 (October 1909): 141-44., 707
  - Turner, Paul Venable. "Frank Lloyd Wright's Other Larkin Building." Journal of the Society of Architectural Historians 39 (1980): 304-6; illus., 708
    The "other" Larkin Company building designed by Wright was an exhibition pavilion for the 1907 Jamestown Tercentennial Exposition Includes bibliographical references.
  - Vaughan, Alden T. "Blacks in Virginia: A Note on the First Decade." William and Mary Quarterly, 3d ser., 29 (1972): 469-78., 709
    Sources from the 1620s suggest that racial prejudice was evident in Virginia even in that very early period after the first arrival of blacksIncludes bibliographical references.
  - ---. "'Expulsion of the Salvages': English Policy and the Virginia Massacre of 1622." William and Mary Quarterly, 3d ser., 35 (1978): 57-84., 710
    This essay seeks to document the patterns of pre-1622 attitudes and policies, to clarify their causal relation to the massacre, and to show the massacre's impact on English perceptions of the Indian and the resultant colonial policy. [Author's note, p. 57]Includes bibliographical references.
  - ---. "The Sad Case of Thomas(ine) Hall." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 86 (1978): 146-48., 711
    In 1629 a court at Jamestown tried to decide the true sex of an individual who had passed as man and woman. Hall was ordered to wear only men's clothing in the futureIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Verner, Coolie. "The First Maps of Virginia, 1590-1673." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 58 (1950): 3-15; maps., 712
    Describes early maps of Virginia from De Bry's engraving based on John White to Augustine Herrman's commission for Lord Baltimore. Includes a list of the various states of John Smith's map.
  - Victory, James. "Jamestown: A Site Selection Exercise." Social Education 46, no. 1 (January 1982): 14-15., 713
    Describes a simulation of the settlement of the Jamestown colony. Students are asked to decide where the colony and fort should be established and to give reasons for selecting or rejecting a particular site.
  - Virginia State Library. "Jamestown Exhibit." In Annual Report of the Library Board of the Virginia State Library, 1906/07, 66-101. Richmond: 1907., 714
    "The Virginia historical manuscript exhibit at the Jamestown Exposition [1907]...was composed of documents drawn from two sources--the State archives, in the Virginia State Library [Library of Virginia], and the Virginia Historical Society."
  - Virginians at Play: A Gallery of Photographs by Harry C. Mann. Virginia Cavalcade 38 (1989): 172-79., 715
    Describes Harry C. Mann's career as a professional photographer, starting with the Jamestown Exposition of 1907 and the establishment of his commercial office in Norfolk, Virginia, in 1908. Mentions the international recognition his photographs garnered, and reprints selected photographs (none of Jamestown or the exposition).
  - Washburn, Wilcomb Edward, ed. "Sir William Berkeley's 'A History of Our Miseries.'" William and Mary Quarterly, 3d ser., 14 (1957): 403-13., 716
    Contains the text of Governor Berkeley's account of Bacon's rebellion in a letter dated February 2, 1676/7, to Henry Coventry, one of Charles II's Principal Secretaries of State.
  - Willard-Mack, Cynthia L., and C. Richard Terman. "Kepone Levels of Selected Terrestrial Animal Species from the Jamestown Island Area." 59th Annual Meeting of the Virginia Academy of Science, Norfolk, May 12-15, 1981., 717
    Comparisons were made of the Kepone levels in the livers of several species of vertebrates from Jamestown Island and from a control area at the College of William and Mary. The data confirm that Kepone contamination of the terrestrial ecosystem is extensive.
  - Wilson, Richard Guy, and Joseph Dye Lahendro. "Larkin Company Jamestown Exhibition Pavilion." Frank Lloyd Wright Newsletter 3, no. 4 (1980): 9; photos., 718
    An exhibition building designed by Wright for the tercentennial celebration in 1907.
  - Wright, Irene A., ed. "Spanish Policy toward Virginia, 1606-1612: Jamestown, Ecija, and John Clark of the Mayflower." American Historical Review 25 (1920): 448-79., 719
    Based on documents in the archives of Seville and Simancas, three of which are transcribed. The Spanish ambassador in London kept his government informed about English activity in Virginia, but the Spanish government took no steps to hinder that activity. Also included is a deposition made in 1611 by John Clark, who had been captured by a Spanish expedition sent to explore the Virginia coast.
  - Wright, Lewis, and Brenda Gardner. "Spiritual Leader to Virginia's First Settlers, Robert Hunt Intended to Spend Only a Few Years in America." The Living Church 208, no. 6 (6 February 1994): 9, 12; illus., 720
    An account of Robert Hunt's life and his brief tenure as first chaplain of the Jamestown settlement.
- Speeches/Lectures
  - Alvey, Edward. Spanish Views of the Settlement at Jamestown: Address Delivered to the Jamestowne Society, November 12, 1977. 1978., 721; 8 pp.
  - Bagby, Ellen Matthews. Brief History Connected with the Organization of the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, As Presented in an Address to the American Association of State Highway Officials at Jamestown, Virginia, November 18, 1932. [1932?], 722; [5] pp.
  - Bayne, Howard Randolph. The Settlement of Jamestown. [1907?], 723; [20] pp.
    A paper read before the Society of Colonial Wars on March 18, 1907.
  - Bemiss, Samuel Merrifield. John Martin of Brandon: Address before the Jamestowne Society, Richmond, Virginia, November 9, 1963., 724; 12 pp.
  - Blake, John Ballard, and Edward Alvey. Two Addresses: John B. Blake, "Of Medical Books and Libraries"; Edward Alvey, "The Assembly Meets at Jamestown, 1619." 1969., 725; 12, 23 pp.
  - Blow, Jennie Matteson Goodell. An Address Delivered before the Daughters of the American Revolution at Their Congress Held in Washington, D. C., April, 1905., 726; 8 pp.
    Mrs. Blow, as chair of the John Smith Monument Committee of the APVA, was seeking support for the monument, though the site and design had not yet been selected.
  - Bowie, Cornelia Magruder. The Jamestowne Story. [1964]., 727; 6 leaves.
    Paper presented to the Washington and Northern Virginia Company of the Jamestowne Society, December 6, 1964.
  - Braxton, Allen Caperton. The Eleventh Amendment: The Address before the Virginia State Bar Association at the Inside Inn, Jamestown Exposition, July 30, 1907., 728; 24 pp.
  - Bryan, John Stewart. Address of Welcome to the Sulgrave Institution, under Auspices of Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, Commemorative of the First Legislative Assembly in America, the Mayflower Compact, the Landing of the Pilgrims; Jamestown Island, Va., October 7, 1920. [1920?], 729; 14 pp.
  - Burton, L. W. The Church at Jamestown, the Norm of American Christianity: An Address Delivered by Lewis W. Burton in Christ Church Cathedral, Lexington, Kentucky, the Third Sunday after Trinity, June 16, 1907, on the Occasion of the Three Hundredth Anniversary of the First Celebration of the Holy Communion at Jamestown, Virginia. [1907?], 730; 15 pp.
  - Bush, Prescott Sheldon. Address...Jamestown Day, Jamestown Island, Virginia, May 9, 1965., 731; 11 pp.
  - Cabell, James Alston. An Address upon the Occasion of Receiving the Memorial Gates of Jamestown, Presented by the Colonial Dames of America to the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities at Jamestown Island, May 9, 1907. [1907]., 732; [4] pp.
  - Cortelyou, George B. Addresses of Secretary Cortelyou: Jamestown Exposition, at the Lee Parade Ground, "West Virginia Day," July 2, 1907; at the Dedication of the West Virginia Coal Column, July 2, 1907; at the Negro Exhibit Building, July 3, 1907. [1907?], 733; 21 pp.
    Cortelyou was U.S. Secretary of the TreasurySee also: Dawson and Cortelyou, Addresses of Governor Dawson and Secretary Cortelyou at the Jamestown Exposition... (ENTRY 736).
  - Craven, Wesley Frank. "...And So the Form of Government Became Perfect." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 77 (1969): 131-45., 734
    This article was read as an address to the Virginia Historical Society at its meeting on January 20, 1969. Craven questions conventional portrayals of the seventeenth-century General Assembly as a bicameral legislature with two relatively equal bodies.
  - ---. White, Red, and Black: The Seventeenth-Century Virginian. Charlottesville: University Press of Virginia, 1971. 114 pp., 735
    The James W. Richard Lectures in History, delivered at the University of Virginia in the fall of 1970 and published in this volume "with only an occasional revision of the text."Includes bibliographical references, and an index.
  - Dawson, William M. O., and George B. Cortelyou. Addresses of Governor Dawson and Secretary Cortelyou at the Jamestown Exposition on West Virginia Day, July 2, 1907. [1907?] 34 pp., 736
    Dawson was Governor of West Virginia; Cortelyou was U.S. Secretary of the TreasurySee also: Addresses of Secretary Cortelyou: Jamestown Exposition...July 2, 1907... (ENTRY 733).
  - Goode, John. "[Speech on the 299th Anniversary of the Settlement of Jamestown.]" In Constitution, By-laws, and List of Officers and Members [Virginians, New York], 1906/1908, 13-31., 737
  - Gray, Gordon. Address...Jamestown Day, Jamestown Island, Virginia, May 14, 1967. [Richmond: 1967]. 15 pp., 738
  - Hall, John Lesslie. Introductory Address Delivered...at the Jamestown Celebration, May 13th, 1891. Richmond: Hill, [1891]. 8 pp., 739
  - ---. Introductory Address Delivered...at the Jamestown Celebration Held May 13th, 1895. [1895?] 8 pp., 740
    "This Celebration was held under the auspices of the College of William and Mary and the Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities."
  - Halsey, Don Peters. The Limits of Centralization: The Address of Hon. Don P. Halsey of the Lynchburg Bar before the Virginia State Bar Association at the Inside Inn, Jamestown Exposition, July 30, 1907. Richmond: Richmond Press, [1907?] 24 pp., 741
  - Hatch, Charles E., Jr. The Jamestown Churches: Talk Given in the Memorial Church at Jamestown for the National Society, Colonial Daughters of the Seventeenth Century. 1957. 9 pp., 742
    Reproduced from typescript.
  - Hazard, Walter. Address...on South Carolina Day at the Jamestown Ter-centennial Exposition, June 28, 1907. Columbia, S. C.: The State Co., 1907. 39 pp., 743
  - Henry, William Wirt. Addresses of W. W. Henry. [1894?] Ca. 175 pp.; portrait., 744
    Includes "The Settlement at Jamestown" (1882) and "The First Legislative Assembly in America" (1894).
  - ---. "The Settlement at Jamestown, with Particular Reference to the Late Attacks upon Captain John Smith, Pocahontas, and John Rolfe [An address delivered before the Virginia Historical Society, February 24, 1882]." In Proceedings of the Virginia Historical Society in Annual Meeting, 1882, 10-63. Richmond: Wm. Ellis Jones, Steam Printer, 1882., 745
    Also published separately and in Addresses of W. W. Henry (ENTRY 744).
  - Keifer, Joseph Warren. The House of Burgesses, and the Development of Legislative Bodies in America: Address of Hon. J. Warren Keifer, Delivered at the Jamestown Exposition, Virginia, July 30, 1907. [1907?] 21 pp., 746
  - Kennedy, Arthur M. Captain John Smith and His Critics. [Philadelphia]: Athenaeum of Philadelphia, 1949. 18 pp., 747
    An address presented at the 134th annual meeting of the Athenaeum of Philadelphia.
  - Lyster, Winifred Lee (Brent). Jamestown: Its Foundation and Ter-centennial. Detroit: Record Printing Co., 1906. 16 pp., 748
    A paper read before the National Society of Colonial Dames in Michigan, January 6, 1906, by Mrs. Henry F. Le Hunte Lyster.
  - Machen, Lewis H. The Duty of the State to Diminish Divorce: The Address of Hon. Lewis H. Machen of Alexandria, Virginia, before the Virginia State Bar Association at the Inside Inn, Jamestown Exposition, July 30, 1907. Richmond: Richmond Press, [1907?] 21 pp., 749
  - Miller, Minor Cline. Spiritual Planting in Virginia: The Emphasis on Religion in the Jamestown Colony. Bridgewater, Va.: Beacon Press, [1957]. 38 pp., 750
    "An address delivered at the meeting of the General Board of the National Council of the Churches of Christ in the United States of America, Williamsburg, Virginia, February 27, 1957."
  - Negro Development and Exposition Company of the United States. An Address to the American Negro. Richmond: [The Company, 1907]. 8 pp., 751
    Library of Congress copy in the Daniel Murray Pamphlet Collection has penciled inscription on cover: Giles B. Jackson, Director Genl.; 1907.
  - Olmstead, Charles Tyler. Jamestown: A Lecture Delivered before the Oneida Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, February 25, 1907. [1907]. 26 pp., 752
  - Page, Thomas Nelson. Address at the Three Hundredth Anniversary of the Settlement of Jamestown. Richmond: Whittet & Shepperson, 1919. 28 pp., 753
  - Parker, Hubert Lister (Baron Parker of Waddington). Magna Carta and the Rule of Law: An Address by Lord Parker of Waddington, Jamestown, Virginia, June 15, 1965. Richmond: Magna Carta Commission of Virginia, [1965]. 18 pp., 754
    At ceremonies commemorating the 750th anniversary of the sealing of Magna CartaBibliography: 17-18.
  - Paschall, Davis Young. Address...Jamestown Day, Jamestown Island, May 12, 1968. [Richmond: APVA, 1968]. 14 pp., 755
  - Poindexter, Charles. Captain John Smith and His Critics: A Lecture before the Society of Geographical and Historical Study of Richmond College. Richmond: [J. L. Hill Printing Co.], 1893. 74 pp., 756
  - Quinn, David B. Address...Jamestown Day, Jamestown Island, May 11, 1969. [Richmond: APVA, 1969]. 29 pp., 757
  - ---. Theory and Practice, Roanoke and Jamestown. Greenville, N.C.: East Carolina University, 1986. 22 pp., 758
    The Lawrence F. Brewster lecture in historyIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Roosevelt, Theodore. [Addresses, 1906-07]. Washington: GPO, [1907]., 759
    Contents include speeches delivered at the opening of the Jamestown Exposition (April 26, 1907), before the National Editorial Association at Jamestown (June 10, 1907), and at the Georgia State building, Jamestown Exposition (June 10, 1907).
  - Speech of Sir Wm. Berkeley, and Declaration of the Assembly, March, 1651. Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 1 (1893): 75-81. From a copy at the Library of Virginia, which was transcribed from a pamphlet copy in the Library of Trinity College, Dublin., 760
    The Speech and Declaration are interesting not only as an expression of one side of opinion in the great political crisis of 1651, when the change of government in England and the passage of the first Navigation Act were stirring the minds of the Virginians, but, also, as illustrating incidentally some facts as to the condition of the people at and before the time of the speech. [From introductory note]
  - Styron, William. An Address by William Styron to the Lower James River Association, Ninth Annual Meeting at Jamestown, October 12, 1986. [Lower James River Association, 1986]. 7 leaves., 761
    Photocopy: [Richmond, Library of Virginia, 1987].
  - Swanson, Claude Augustus. Addresses...Jamestown Island, May 13, 1907; Jamestown Exposition, June 12, 1907. Richmond: Davis Bottom, Superintendent of Public Printing, 1907. 15 pp., 762
    Claude A. Swanson was Governor of Virginia. The June 12 address was delivered on Virginia Day at the Jamestown ExpositionThe Virginia Day address was also published in 1912 in U.S. Senate Doc. 948, 62d Cong., 2d sess.
  - Thomas, Richard Samuel. The Religious Element in the Settlement at Jamestown in 1607: Historical Address Delivered before the Sixth Annual Council of the Diocese of Southern Virginia, June 10th, 1898. Petersburg, Va.: Franklin Press, 1898. 36 pp., 763
  - Towne, Charles A. The Jamestown Exposition: Address on Celebration of Three Hundredth Anniversary of Landing of First Colonists of Virginia. Washington: 1906. 16 pp., 764
    April 10, 1906.
  - Troubetzkoy, Ulrich, ed. Significant Addresses of the Jamestown Festival, 1957. Richmond: U.S. Jamestown-Williamsburg-Yorktown Celebration Commission, 1958. 75 pp., 765
    A selection of addresses delivered in connection with the 1957 celebration, including those by Richard M. Nixon and Queen Elizabeth IIWith a foreword by John Melville Jennings.
  - Tucker, Henry St. George. Address at the Opening of the Jamestown Exposition, the Ter-centennial Celebration of the Founding of the First Permanent Settlement of the English People in America, on Hampton Roads, Virginia, April 26th, 1907. [Norfolk: Burke & Gregory, 1907]. 22 pp., 766
  - ---. "Jamestown: Paradise or Pest Hole." Transactions of the American Clinical and Climatological Association 86 (1974): 1-10; graphs., 767
    The speaker, in his presidential address to the Association, reviews the seventeenth-century history of the Jamestown settlement, with emphasis on disease and medical issues.
  - Tyler, Lyon Gardiner. Address of President Lyon G. Tyler on the Occasion of the Celebration by William and Mary College and the A.P.V.A. of the First Settlement of Jamestown, May 13, 1895. [Richmond: Printed for private distribution by J. H. Whitty, 1895]. 6 pp.; folded map., 768
  - Whitehill, Walter Muir. Address...Jamestown Day, Jamestown Island, Virginia, May 15, 1966. 16 pp., 769
  - ---. "Cerebration Versus Celebration." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 68 (1960): 259-70., 770
    An address delivered at the annual meeting of the Virginia Historical Society, May 1960. At the advent of the Civil War centennial, the speaker explores the influence of crass commercialism on historical societies and celebrations. The Jamestown Exposition of 1907 is an example.
  - Williams, John Skelton. Address Delivered Richmond Day, July 18, 1907, at the Jamestown Exposition. [Richmond: Richmond Press, 1907?] 27 pp., 771
  - Winborne, Benjamin B. Speech of Hon. Benj. B. Winborne of Murfreesboro, N.C., Delivered at the Convention of Peanut Growers of Virginia, North Carolina and Tennessee, at the Jamestown Exposition, Friday, Sept. 27, 1907. Raleigh, N.C.: Edwards & Broughton Printing Co., [1907?] 15 pp., 772
- Pamphlets/Broadsides
  - American Federation of Labor. Industrial and Social Economic Exhibit at the Jamestown Ter-centennial Exposition, in Social Economy Building at Norfolk, Va. Washington: The Federation, [1907?] 20 pp.; illus., 773
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities. The Founding of the Colony at Jamestown. Richmond: Whittet & Shepperson, [1921]. [4] pp., 774
  - ---. Jamestown, Birthplace of a Nation. [Washington: GPO, 1955]. [8] pp.; illus., map., 775
    Prepared by the APVA in cooperation with the National Park Service.